Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Loy Baxter Papers, 1954-1978, bulk 1966-1967
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Loy Baxter papers 1954-1978, bulk 1966-1967
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company.
1.8 linear feet Extent: 1200 Items
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. Loy Baxter was an executive who held a range of positions during a 30 year career with JWT, including General Manager of JWT Mexico; Management Supervisor and Director of Public Relations of JWT New York; and Manager of the Western District (U.S.). The Loy Baxter Papers span the years 1954-1968, the bulk of which document the period 1966-1967, and include correspondence, clippings, corporation records, photographs, promotional materials, newsletters, press releases, public relations campaign proposals, speeches, and a long-playing record. The collection primarily documents Baxter's work with the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) as management supervisor and director of public relations. JWT public relations clients represented in the collection include Alcan Aluminum Corporation; Eastman Kodak Company; Liggett & Myers Tobacco Company; National Dairy Products Corporation, Kraft Foods Division; Trailways; and the U.S. Marine Corps.
RL.00666
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Loy Baxter Papers were received by the Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library as a gift in 1996.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1915 April 9 Born Loy Joseph Baxter, Indianapolis, Ind.
1937 Recieved Bachelor's degree from Indiana University
1937-1940 Owned and published the college humor magazine Bored Walk; owned Board Walk Publishing Company
1939-1940 Copywriter and editor, Kingan and Company meat packers, Indianapolis, Ind.,
1940-1945 Served in the Infantry Reserve in the United States Army. Discharged as Lieutenant Colonel.
1946 Copywriter and Assistant Advertising Manager, Mohawk Carpet Mills, Amsterdam, N.Y.
1947 July Joined J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT), Washington, D.C. office
1948 Son Jeff Baxter born
1950 Manager, JWT Washington, D.C.
1958 Writer, Public Relations Dept., JWT New York
1960 General Manager, JWT Mexico
1964 Management Supervisor and Director of Public Relations, JWT New York
1965 Elected Vice President of JWT; supervised Aluminum, Ltd., U.S. Playing Card Company, and Gorton's accounts
1971 Manager, JWT Los Angeles
1973 Manager, JWT Western Region
1974-1975 Member of the board of directors, Ad Club of Los Angeles
1977 August Retired from JWT
2003 March 15 Died in Los Angeles
After retiring from JWT, Baxter worked as chairman of advertising research firm Phase One in Los Angeles. Baxter was married to Cathryn Rose.
Collection Overview
The Loy Baxter Papers span the years 1954-1968, the bulk of which document the period 1966-1967, and include correspondence, clippings, corporation records, photographs, promotional materials, newsletters, press releases, public relations campaign proposals, speeches, and a long-playing record. The collection primarily documents Baxter's work with the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) as management supervisor and director of public relations. JWT public relations clients represented in the collection include Alcan; Eastman Kodak; Liggett & Myers; the National Dairy Products Corporation, Kraft Foods Division; Trailways; and the U.S. Marine Corps.
The collection is organized into two series: Office Files and Account Files. The Office Files Series chiefly documents communication between Baxter and other JWT offices. Other files in this series document events; projects; or relationships with organizations, such as the JWT subsidiary Lexington International, which specialized in creating press releases and industrial publicity for clients. The Account Files Series documents Baxter's involvement with JWT public relations clients and client campaigns. Includes a set of essays commissioned for an Alcan Corporation advertising campaign written by public leaders U Thant, Edward J. Louge, and Columbus O'Donnell Iselin. The essays, written for magazine publication, shared the common theme of major challenges that affect humanity.
Subject Headings
Baxter, Loy, 1915-2003; J. Walter Thompson Company; J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office; Alcan Aluminum Corporation; Eastman Kodak Company; Liggett & Myers Tobacco Company; National Dairy Products Corporation. Kraft Foods Division; Continental Trailways, Inc.; United States. Marine Corps; Advertising -- Customer relations; Advertising -- History -- 20th century; Advertising -- Management; Advertising -- Public relations; Advertising agencies -- Management; Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising campaigns; Advertising executives; Corporations -- Public relations; Industrial publicity; Clippings; Newsletters; Phonograph records; Photographs; Press releases; Promotional materials; Proposals; Sound recordings; Speeches; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Related Material
Materials related to this collection may be found in other Hartman Center collections within the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives, including the Account Files Collection; the Newsletter Collection; Biographical Information; Public Relations Department Records; and the W. Lee Preschel Papers
Contents of Collection
- Office Files Series, 1954-1977, (1 Box)
  Consists of correspondence, clippings, corporation records, photographs, and promotional materials that document Baxter's work as management supervisor and director of public relations for JWT in New York. Many of the files document communication between Baxter and other JWT offices from 1966-1967; while others document events; projects; or relationships with organizations. Arranged alphabetically by file name, and therin in reverse chronological order.
  - Australia, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Canada, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Caracas trip, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Chicago, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Detroit, 1967 (Box 1)
  - International research, 1954-1970 (Box 1)
  - JWT Communications Program Second Quarter Review, 1976 (Box 1)
  - JWT Worldwide Research Directory, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Lexington International, 1967 (Box 1)
  - London, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Mexico City, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - New York Press Photographers Association, 1967 (Box 1)
  - San Francisco, 1966 (Box 1)
  - San Franc`isco, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Shachte, Henry, 1964-1967 (Box 1)
  - Supermarket Analysis and Industry Trends, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Washington, 1967 (Box 1)
  - World Journal Tribune project, 1967 (Box 1)
- Account Files, 1966-1976, (2 Boxes)
  Consists of correspondence, clippings, newsletters, press releases, public relations campaign proposals, speeches and promotional materials that document Baxter's involvement with JWT public relations clients and client campaigns. Also includes a long-playing record created by Youth Concepts. Includes a set of essays commissioned for an Alcan Corporation advertising campaign written by public leaders U Thant, Edward J. Louge, and Columbus O'Donnell Iselin. The essays, written for magazine publication, shared the common theme of major challenges that affect humanity. Arranged alphabetically by client name, and therein in reverse chronological order.
  - Alcan Aluminum Corporation, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Alcan Aluminum Limited, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Alcan essays, 1967 (Box 2)
  - American Gas Association, 1967 (Box 2)
  - American Machine and Foundry (AMF), 1967 (Box 2)
  - Association Hospital Service, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Burroughs Corporation, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Carte Blanche, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Champion, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Dean Witter and Company, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Eastman Chemical Products, Inc., 1967 (Box 2)
  - Eastman Kodak, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Electronics and Alloys, Inc., 1967 (Box 2)
  - Gorton Corporation, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Johnson Motors, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Kawasaki Motors Corporation, 1976 Apr. 14 (Box 2)
  - Kodak Mexicana, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Kraft Foods, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Liggett and Myers, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - New York Academy of Sciences, 1967 (Box 2)
  - New York Public Library, 1967 (Box 3)
  - National Dairy Products Corporation (Kraft), 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - National fisheries, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Public Relations Committee of the Fair Campaign Practices Committee, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Reader's Digest, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Salas, E. Guillermo, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Standard Brands, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Standard Brands International, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Trailways, 1966-1967, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - U.S. Brewers Association, 1967 (Box 3)
  - U.S. Marine Corps, 1967 (Box 3)
  - U.S. Playing Cards, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Warner-Lambert Pharmaceutical Company, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Water and waste industries, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Youth Concepts, 1967-1968 (Box 3)